<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc [
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
]>
<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
     category="info"
     docName="draft-vicente-acme-pqc-agility-profile-01"
     ipr="trust200902"
     submissionType="independent"
     xml:lang="en"
     version="3">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="ACME PQC Agility Profile">Post-Quantum Cryptographic Agility Profile for ACME</title>

    <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-vicente-acme-pqc-agility-profile-01"/>

    <author initials="B." surname="Vicente" fullname="Brian Vicente">
      <organization>Sanctum SecOps LLC</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <city>Pine City</city>
          <region>NY</region>
          <country>United States of America</country>
        </postal>
        <email>bvicente@sanctumsecops.com</email>
        <uri>https://orcid.org/0009-0006-6395-5308</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2026" month="June" day="9"/>

    <area>Security</area>
    <workgroup>Automated Certificate Management Environment</workgroup>

    <keyword>post-quantum cryptography</keyword>
    <keyword>PQC</keyword>
    <keyword>ACME</keyword>
    <keyword>agility profile</keyword>
    <keyword>hybrid certificate</keyword>
    <keyword>rotation epoch</keyword>
    <keyword>tenant isolation</keyword>
    <keyword>composite chain policy</keyword>
    <keyword>posture scoring</keyword>
    <keyword>Sanctum SecOps</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>
        This document defines a Post-Quantum Cryptographic (PQC) Agility Profile extension
        for the Automated Certificate Management Environment (ACME) [RFC8555]. The extension
        introduces a typed pqcAgility object that an ACME server includes in its
        directory metadata and that an ACME client may embed in an order object to express
        per-order PQC policy. The object carries: a ranked list of PQC algorithm preferences;
        a hybrid_required enforcement bit; a rotation_epoch_id binding
        certificates to a coordinated migration epoch; an optional
        composite_chain_policy identifier governing composite-signature chain
        construction; and an optional pqc_posture_score reflecting the requestor's
        cryptographic-readiness assessment.
      </t>
      <t>
        This document defines the semantic content of a named PQC profile and is intended
        to complement the generic ACME Profiles Extension
        [I-D.ietf-acme-profiles], which specifies the profile-selection mechanism
        (an opaque profile name string in the order object) but does not define the
        PQC-specific fields that give that selection cryptographic meaning.
        It does not modify the core ACME state machine or account management flows
        defined in RFC 8555.
      </t>
      <t>
        Multi-tenant ACME deployments MUST enforce tenant isolation of
        pqcAgility directives. Concrete isolation parameters are
        deployment-specific and are intentionally out of scope.
      </t>
    </abstract>

    <note title="Relationship to Other Documents" removeInRFC="true">
      <t>
        This document is distinct from and does not conflict with
        draft-giron-acme-pqcnegotiation (expired 2024-08-19, individual submission),
        which defines a pre-account /cert-algorithms discovery endpoint and
        KEMTLS certificate issuance modes. That document addresses algorithm
        capability advertisement before account creation. This document addresses
        per-order PQC enforcement policy, hybrid mandates, rotation epoch binding,
        composite chain governance, posture scoring, and tenant isolation.
      </t>
      <t>
        This document is also distinct from the ACME Profiles Extension
        [I-D.ietf-acme-profiles], which defines a generic, algorithm-agnostic
        profile selection string mechanism. This document defines the typed PQC
        semantic fields that populate a PQC-named profile within that framework.
        The two documents are complementary: an ACME server MAY expose a profile
        named (for example) "pqc-hybrid-ml-dsa-65" whose content and enforcement
        semantics are defined by this document, while the selection mechanism is
        provided by [I-D.ietf-acme-profiles].
      </t>
    </note>

    <note title="Source and Archival" removeInRFC="true">
      <t>
        Source for this draft is maintained at
        <eref target="https://github.com/Sanc-Admin/acme-pqc-agility-profile">https://github.com/Sanc-Admin/acme-pqc-agility-profile</eref>.
        A citable archival version of this document is published at Zenodo
        upon each tagged release.
        Author ORCID iD:
        <eref target="https://orcid.org/0009-0006-6395-5308">https://orcid.org/0009-0006-6395-5308</eref>.
        Author professional credentials:
        <eref target="https://www.credly.com/users/brian-vicente">https://www.credly.com/users/brian-vicente</eref>.
      </t>
      <t>
        Discussion of this document occurs on the IETF "acme" mailing list
        (acme@ietf.org). Issues and pull requests may be filed at the GitHub
        repository linked above.
      </t>
    </note>

    <note title="IPR Considerations" removeInRFC="true">
      <t>
        The author has filed United States patent applications covering
        subject matter relevant to this document, including
        U.S. Provisional Patent Application No. 64/080,137
        (filed 2026-06-01) and U.S. Patent Application No. 19/698,870
        (filed 2026-06-05). By posting this Internet-Draft, the author
        submits to the IETF Trust the rights described in Section 5 of
        BCP 78 and BCP 79. Patent licensing terms are not yet known.
        Implementers and reviewers should consult the IETF Datatracker
        IPR disclosure page for this document for current disclosure status.
        The Sanctum SecOps Private Enterprise Number (PEN) root used for
        any OID allocations referenced in companion documents is
        1.3.6.1.4.1.65953.
      </t>
      <t>
        Patent-Pending Claim Scope Notice: The pending patent applications
        referenced above cover orchestration, observability, and
        tenant-isolation mechanisms in multi-tenant PKI systems as they
        intersect the claims of those applications. The per-order
        pqcAgility object structure, rotation_epoch_id
        field semantics, hybrid_required enforcement bit, and
        pqc_posture_score field are among the elements relevant
        to those applications. This Internet-Draft does not grant any
        patent license. Implementation parameters that extend beyond the
        disclosed interface (including but not limited to scoring weights,
        rotation triggers, tenant carve-out parameters, and adequacy
        thresholds) are intentionally out of scope of this document.
      </t>
    </note>

  </front>

  <middle>

    <section anchor="introduction">
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>
        ACME [RFC8555] is the dominant protocol for automated certificate issuance.
        As the Internet migrates toward post-quantum cryptography (PQC) and hybrid
        certificate chains, ACME deployments require a structured way to express
        per-order PQC enforcement policy beyond simple algorithm capability
        advertisement.
      </t>
      <t>
        Existing work addresses adjacent but distinct problems. The expired individual
        submission draft-giron-acme-pqcnegotiation defines a pre-account
        /cert-algorithms capability discovery endpoint and KEMTLS certificate
        issuance modes, but does not define per-order policy objects, hybrid enforcement
        mandates, rotation epoch bindings, composite chain policy, posture scoring, or
        tenant isolation requirements. The ACME Profiles Extension
        [I-D.ietf-acme-profiles] defines a generic, algorithm-agnostic profile
        selection mechanism using an opaque profile name string, but does not specify
        the PQC-semantic content those profiles carry.
      </t>
      <t>
        This document fills the gap by defining the typed pqcAgility object
        -- the PQC-semantic payload that an ACME server advertises and an ACME client
        attaches to an order to enforce a specific cryptographic agility posture.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="terminology">
      <name>Terminology</name>
      <t>
        The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
        "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in
        BCP 14 [RFC2119] [RFC8174] when, and only when, they appear in all
        capitals, as shown here.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="pqcagility-object">
      <name>The pqcAgility Object</name>

      <section anchor="fields">
        <name>Field Definitions</name>
        <dl>
          <dt>pqc_algorithm_preferences (array of string, OPTIONAL):</dt>
          <dd>An ordered list of PQC algorithm identifiers, most preferred first.
          The server MUST select from the intersection of advertised and requested
          algorithms. If the intersection is empty, the server MUST reject the order
          with an unsupportedPQCAlgorithm problem document.</dd>

          <dt>hybrid_required (boolean, OPTIONAL, default false):</dt>
          <dd>When true in directory metadata, the server REQUIRES all certificates
          under this profile to use a hybrid composite signature. A client setting
          this true in an order asserts a requirement for hybrid issuance; the server
          MUST honor this or reject the order. This enforcement bit is distinct from
          the algorithm selection mechanism in draft-giron-acme-pqcnegotiation,
          which does not define a server-side mandatory hybrid enforcement gate.</dd>

          <dt>rotation_epoch_id (string, OPTIONAL):</dt>
          <dd>An opaque server-defined string identifying the migration epoch cohort.
          Epoch identifiers coordinate certificate renewals across account populations
          toward a common PQC algorithm baseline. Not defined in any prior ACME draft.</dd>

          <dt>composite_chain_policy (string, OPTIONAL):</dt>
          <dd>A server-defined identifier referencing composite-chain construction
          rules governing which classical algorithm is paired with which PQC algorithm
          at each chain tier. Not defined in any prior ACME draft.</dd>

          <dt>pqc_posture_score (integer, OPTIONAL):</dt>
          <dd>An integer in [0, 100] reflecting the cryptographic-readiness posture
          of the account or deployment. A score of 100 indicates full PQC-native
          capability. The scoring methodology is deployment-specific. Not defined
          in any prior ACME draft.</dd>
        </dl>
      </section>

      <section anchor="directory-advertisement">
        <name>Directory Advertisement</name>
        <t>
          An ACME server compliant with this profile MUST include a pqcAgility
          object in its directory metadata when offering PQC agility profiles.
          Example directory metadata fragment:
        </t>
        <artwork><![CDATA[
{
  "meta": {
    "pqcAgility": {
      "pqc_algorithm_preferences": [
        "id-ML-DSA-65",
        "id-ML-DSA-44",
        "id-SLH-DSA-SHA2-128s"
      ],
      "hybrid_required": true,
      "rotation_epoch_id": "2026-Q3-hybrid-baseline",
      "composite_chain_policy": "sanctum-pqc-cp-v1",
      "pqc_posture_score": null
    }
  }
}
        ]]></artwork>
      </section>

      <section anchor="order-object-extensions">
        <name>Order Object Extensions</name>
        <t>
          An ACME client MAY include a pqcAgility member in a new-order request.
          Example new-order payload fragment:
        </t>
        <artwork><![CDATA[
{
  "identifiers": [
    {"type": "dns", "value": "example.org"}
  ],
  "pqcAgility": {
    "pqc_algorithm_preferences": ["id-ML-DSA-65"],
    "hybrid_required": true,
    "rotation_epoch_id": "2026-Q3-hybrid-baseline",
    "composite_chain_policy": "sanctum-pqc-cp-v1",
    "pqc_posture_score": 87
  }
}
        ]]></artwork>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="tenant-isolation">
      <name>Tenant Isolation</name>
      <t>
        Multi-tenant ACME servers MUST ensure that pqcAgility directives
        from one account do not influence issuance decisions for other accounts.
        In particular:
      </t>
      <ul>
        <li>A rotation_epoch_id submitted by one account MUST NOT alter the
        epoch assignment of any other account.</li>
        <li>A composite_chain_policy identifier supplied by one tenant MUST NOT
        cause non-default chain construction policy for other tenants.</li>
        <li>A pqc_posture_score provided by one account MUST NOT be used as
        eligibility input for any other account.</li>
      </ul>
      <t>
        Concrete tenant-isolation implementation parameters are deployment-specific
        and are intentionally out of scope of this document.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="relationship-to-prior-work">
      <name>Relationship to Prior and Concurrent Work</name>

      <section anchor="giron-distinction">
        <name>Distinction from draft-giron-acme-pqcnegotiation</name>
        <t>
          draft-giron-acme-pqcnegotiation-03 (expired 2024-08-19, no WG adoption)
          defines a /cert-algorithms discovery endpoint and KEMTLS issuance modes.
          It does not define: per-order policy objects; a hybrid_required enforcement
          bit; rotation epoch binding; composite chain policy identifiers; PQC posture
          scoring; or multi-tenant isolation requirements. This document addresses
          those gaps and is not a competing mechanism.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="acme-profiles-relationship">
        <name>Relationship to draft-ietf-acme-profiles</name>
        <t>
          The ACME Profiles Extension [I-D.ietf-acme-profiles] defines a generic
          mechanism for servers to advertise named certificate profiles and for clients
          to select a profile via an opaque string. It does not define PQC-semantic
          content. This document defines that content. Servers MAY expose PQC agility
          profiles named per [I-D.ietf-acme-profiles] whose enforcement is defined here.
          The pqcAgility object MAY appear alongside the profile field from
          [I-D.ietf-acme-profiles] in an order object.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="lamps-pquip-relationship">
        <name>Relationship to LAMPS and PQUIP Work</name>
        <t>
          The hybrid_required bit and composite_chain_policy identifiers are designed
          to interoperate with [I-D.ietf-lamps-pq-composite-sigs] and
          [I-D.ietf-pquip-hybrid-signature-spectrums]. This document defines how an
          ACME server enforces and advertises selection of those formats via the
          order lifecycle.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="security-considerations">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>
        This document builds upon the security model of RFC 8555. The extensions
        do not modify account management or identifier validation flows.
        PQC posture metadata (pqc_posture_score) is sensitive. Servers SHOULD
        avoid exposing aggregated tenant PQC posture without authorization.
        The rotation_epoch_id field MUST NOT be used to correlate accounts across
        tenants. Servers SHOULD treat client-supplied posture scores as advisory only.
        The hybrid_required enforcement bit creates a migration dependency; server
        operators SHOULD announce hybrid-required profiles with sufficient lead time
        via rotation_epoch_id.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="iana-considerations">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>
        IANA is requested to create a new registry group,
        "Automated Certificate Management Environment (ACME) PQC Agility Profile",
        containing:
      </t>
      <ul>
        <li>"ACME PQC Agility Algorithm Identifiers" (Specification Required)</li>
        <li>"ACME PQC Composite Chain Policy Identifiers" (Expert Review)</li>
        <li>"ACME PQC Agility Error Types": initial entry unsupportedPQCAlgorithm (Specification Required)</li>
      </ul>
      <t>
        IANA is also requested to add pqcAgility (object) to the
        "ACME Directory Metadata Fields" registry and to the
        "ACME Order Object Fields" registry (Configurable: true).
        Reference: this document.
      </t>
    </section>

  </middle>

  <back>
    <references>
      <name>References</name>

      <references>
        <name>Normative References</name>
        <reference anchor="RFC2119" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc2119">
          <front>
            <title>Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels</title>
            <author initials="S." surname="Bradner" fullname="S. Bradner"/>
            <date year="1997" month="March"/>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="RFC8174" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8174">
          <front>
            <title>Ambiguity of Uppercase vs Lowercase in RFC 2119 Key Words</title>
            <author initials="B." surname="Leiba" fullname="B. Leiba"/>
            <date year="2017" month="May"/>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="RFC8555" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8555">
          <front>
            <title>Automatic Certificate Management Environment (ACME)</title>
            <author initials="R." surname="Barnes" fullname="R. Barnes"/>
            <author initials="J." surname="Hoffman-Andrews" fullname="J. Hoffman-Andrews"/>
            <author initials="D." surname="McCarney" fullname="D. McCarney"/>
            <author initials="J." surname="Kasten" fullname="J. Kasten"/>
            <date year="2019" month="March"/>
          </front>
        </reference>
      </references>

      <references>
        <name>Informative References</name>
        <reference anchor="I-D.ietf-acme-profiles"
                   target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-ietf-acme-profiles/">
          <front>
            <title>Automated Certificate Management Environment (ACME) Profiles Extension</title>
            <author initials="A." surname="Gable" fullname="Aaron Gable"/>
            <date year="2026" month="March"/>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="I-D.ietf-lamps-pq-composite-sigs"
                   target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-ietf-lamps-pq-composite-sigs/">
          <front>
            <title>Composite ML-DSA for use in Internet PKI</title>
            <author initials="M." surname="Ounsworth" fullname="Mike Ounsworth"/>
            <date year="2025"/>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="I-D.ietf-pquip-hybrid-signature-spectrums"
                   target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-ietf-pquip-hybrid-signature-spectrums/">
          <front>
            <title>Hybrid signature spectrums</title>
            <author initials="D." surname="Connolly" fullname="Deirdre Connolly"/>
            <date year="2025"/>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="I-D.giron-acme-pqcnegotiation"
                   target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-giron-acme-pqcnegotiation/">
          <front>
            <title>ACME PQC Algorithm Negotiation (expired)</title>
            <author initials="A.A." surname="Giron" fullname="Alexandre Augusto Giron"/>
            <date year="2024" month="February"/>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="NIST-FIPS-204"
                   target="https://doi.org/10.6028/NIST.FIPS.204">
          <front>
            <title>Module-Lattice-Based Digital Signature Standard (FIPS 204)</title>
            <author><organization>NIST</organization></author>
            <date year="2024" month="August"/>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="NIST-IR-8547"
                   target="https://doi.org/10.6028/NIST.IR.8547.ipd">
          <front>
            <title>Transition to Post-Quantum Cryptography Standards (NIST IR 8547)</title>
            <author><organization>NIST</organization></author>
            <date year="2024" month="November"/>
          </front>
        </reference>
      </references>
    </references>
  </back>

</rfc>